Hello and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan.
And today we're going to be
looking at reduction reactions
of aldehydes and ketones for
introductory organic chemistry.
So what we're going to be specifically
looking at is aldehydes and ketones
are reduced by the addition of hydrogen
in the presence of a metal catalyst.
Meaning that when, when we say that
word reduced, what we want to be able
to think about is reducing the number
of oxygens And add, adding hydrogens.
So if I have, let's say the following
example here, where what, what we're going
to be doing is reducing the number of CO
bonds by essentially opening the doors
like how we did in an addition reaction.
So simply, we're going to be
taking our aldehydes and ketones
and turning them into alcohols.
So just by showing, let's say, a
little example like this, right,
we're changing the double bond to
an alcohol, so reducing CO bonds.
So in this video, we're going to
go through mechanisms, trying to
understand that entire reduction
process for us to, and going
through multiple examples of that.
So please stay tuned and let's
go into how this reaction works.
Okay, so the basic
mechanism is just like this.
So it's similar to an addition reaction.
Or if you remember from that
previous video, it was all about
trying to open up our double doors.
So meaning if I have a double bond, CO
double bond, we're going to be opening
it up just like a little cabinet.
And when I open that up, we're going
to be adding something to each part.
So if I have my bond here, the way
that this is going to be shown is that
we're going to have a reducing agent.
That is going to be changing this
particular and causing this reaction.
So typically it's written with an H.
Sometimes you might see it written
with an R as well to represent, hey,
this is going through reduction.
There will typically be some
kind of catalyst as well.
Depending on your class, every
teacher is a little different.
They might try to tell you
exactly how much you need to know.
So, if we redraw our carbon
structure, the only thing that is
changing is our functional groups.
But we are also adding two components.
So, as I mentioned, we're going
to be opening up the doors.
So, that is our double bond here.
Notice how we're opening it up.
And what we're going to be doing
here is, as we open up those doors,
we are adding hydrogen, right?
So, we're adding hydrogens
to the double bond, uh, just
like I have written up here.
So, when we open that, we
can see that, okay, here's a
hydrogen on each individual part.
So we have on the left hand
side an aldehyde turning into a
primary alcohol when that happens.
Okay, so aldehyde goes towards a
primary alcohol, and that is for
this particular reduction example.
Let's go on to, into both of these looking
at aldehydes and ketones specifically.
So like we were just doing previously,
you can see that an aldehyde, we are
opening up those doors and we're adding
on the hydrogens onto each component.
So an aldehyde is always going
to turn into a primary alcohol.
Now what about ketones?
Well ketones can also reduce as well.
So a ketone, being that it's in the
middle of the chain, this is going
to turn into a secondary alcohol.
It's going to be the same general
reaction though, we're going to
be opening up those double doors
on our carbon carbon double bond.
So what we're going to do is take
our CO, we're going to just slightly
move around our R groups just to help
make room for our cabinets to open.
We'll put a door on each carbon and
oxygen and what we're going to be
doing is adding a hydrogen to each one.
So as you can see, we go to a secondary
alcohol versus primary just to kind of
review what that means in case maybe you
don't remember from organic chemistry
or previous weeks in your courses.
So the whole idea is that, okay, when we
have, let's go to the primary example,
is if we go to this carbon that's
attached to the alcohol, you're going
to count how many R groups there are
next to the carbon with your alcohol.
So what I usually do is put a little star.
And I count how many R
groups there are next to it.
So this top one is a primary versus this
one we star the carbon with the alcohol
and we see one and then two is how we
would look at this particular reduction.
So primary and secondary
alcohols can reduce.
Sometimes you can also see where a
carboxylic acid can reduce as well,
where that can go to an aldehyde and
then to a primary alcohol as well.
Let's go through a bunch of
examples and try to understand
and review this process together.
So, in a lot of your chemistry classes,
the way that these are going to be
presented to you is to predict the
products of the following reaction,
which is a common exam, quiz,
homework problem that you'll see in an
introductory organic chemistry course.
So, for this one, what we have for the
very first one, we can see, we, the first
thing we have to do is identify what is
our functional group, and so that way we
have an idea of, well, what do we expect?
Well, we can see that we have the C double
bond O, and it's in the middle of a chain.
So whenever it is in the middle,
this is our ketone, right?
So in this case, what
does the ketone turn into?
Well, if you can remember how is
the functional group changing, it
can help guide your thinking and how
exactly to pick your final answer.
So ketone is going to
go to a primary alcohol.
So when we do this, remember from
before we're going to be opening up
the double door on our double bond.
So when that opens, we're adding a
hydrogen to each individual part.
So let's redraw our structure, right?
So keeping the base
compound portions here.
And then now we're going to draw
our doors on the carbon that this
O is connected to as well as the,
the carbon and the oxygen, right?
And now what was the whole idea
with reduction is we're adding
a hydrogen to each component.
So just like this, we have now
an extra hydrogen on each part.
So just to kind of clean that up for
ourselves, because it looks a little
wonky, it's going to be the same
thing as saying, hey, we have this 2-
propanol is what is going to be created
from the reduction of 2- propanone.
So it goes from 2-
propanone to 2- propanol.
Now, with the next one, alright, well
it's the same general idea, right?
We have a benzaldehyde
here, so benzaldehyde.
How will that go through
a reduction oxidation?
We want to go through that entire
little checklist for ourselves.
So being that it's an aldehyde, a
double bond, it can reduce, right?
So same thing as before, we're
going to be essentially opening
up that little double bond.
So let's make this a
little easier on ourselves.
We'll copy and paste the structure here.
So by opening up the double bond, what
we will do is we will draw new lines to
help represent our two cabinet doors.
And we're going to be adding
hydrogen to each component.
So when we do that, we have now
an alcohol here that's attached
to our, um, to our benzene ring.
So we have a benzyl alcohol here.
So it's a little bit different
than a phenol because we have
that extra carbon in the middle.
All right, let's try another example.
So if I have the following one,
well, once again, we have an alcohol
and it says it's being reduced.
Well, how do we exactly do that one?
I don't remember kind of going
over an example like that.
So sometimes You're given a
reaction that just can't happen.
So if you remember reduction occurs
if you have a Ketone, it'll go to
a two prime alcohol and aldehyde
will go to a one prime or a primary
alcohol in this case You are starting
with a primary alcohol Meaning
that it can't go through reduction.
So what are we going to do?
We're going to write no reaction
to help illustrate that process.
Now, and sometimes you might be
given an example where you have to
show both directions that can go.
So if you reviewed my previous
video on oxidation, then you
should be able to do this one too.
And if not, then go, go review it.
So that way it'll help remind you.
Cause this is a very common
thing where you have to do.
different reactions.
So let's do the one
that we do know, right?
We just went over reduction.
So right here I have an aldehyde.
So we can see we have a, um, ethanol here.
So it's a two carbon aldehyde.
So what is that going to be doing?
It's going to reduce, we're
going to open up those doors.
So when that happens, we will
turn the aldehyde into an alcohol.
Making ethanol.
Right.
So the alcohol that many, many of us
potentially enjoy from time to time.
Right?
Aldehyde to an alcohol with
where we make a ethanol.
Alright, now is that it?
Well, we have this other part
here all about oxidation.
So how does the oxidation portion happen?
Well, instead of us removing
oxygen, So, and just to kind of re
to review that, what we, we will
review that thing that I mentioned
earlier is removing oxygen at oxygen.
Adding oxygen.
So here at the very beginning,
we had two co bonds.
Now how do I have two?
Well, if we zoom in on this aldehyde,
we can color in the two lines here
and we can number them as one and two.
So you had two bonds.
When in the, uh, out in the
reduced structure, notice
that we only have one CO bond.
So you go from one, so you went from
two to one, you reduced the number of
CO bonds, right, or you added hydrogen.
Now, when it comes to oxidation,
it's all about adding oxygen.
So we have, we have three CO bonds.
In this particular case, I'll
go to a C double bond O with an
OH group or a carboxylic acid.
So in this case, it's going to make acetic
acid or also commonly known as vinegar.
So you can go from ethanol all
the way over to acetic acid.
So a very large different
opportunity of reactions.
So this has been the world of reduction.
I hope this video helped you.
And if it did, please hit that like and
subscribe button and please comment below
if you'd like to see future videos and
to let me know what you think about them.
And remember, these are
for introductory chemistry.
They're meant to just kind of give
you a basic idea of reduction.
Um, hope this will help you
practice problems and to do more.
This has been Dr.
Dan and I like to see you all later.
Bye now.